Guide to the Henry Raup Wagner Collection of Texas Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Original Documents, Dates 1707-1847; Series I; 1.5; (3 boxes)
  - San Antonio, Texas. Jefe Politico.
    - LS to Governer of Coahuila and Texas, Bejar, Texas., 1831 Nov 19 (Box 3, Folder 83)
      3 p. 20 cm. and enclosures 8 p. 25 cm. Signed: Ramon Musquiz Encloses reports of Martin de Leon, Manuel de los Santos Coy, and Frost Thorn on colonization of Guadalupe Victoria and Nacogdoches.
  - Austin, John, 1801-1833.
    - ALS to J.D. Bradburn, Comandante, Anahuac, Brazos Bar, Texas., 1831 Dec 27 (Box 3, Folder 84)
      2 p. 20 cm. Sewn together with a copy of letter from S.F. Austin to Bradburn, 1831 Dec 30, Brazoria, and LS from Bradburn to Gen. Teran, 1831 Mar 4, Anahuac. 8 p. 33 cm. On customs administration and politics. Copy, transcription, and translation of LS from Bradburn to Teran available. See Series II, Box 4, folder 144.
  - Austin, Stephen Fuller, 1793-1836.
    - ALS to Comandante General, Estados Internos de Oriente, San Felipe de Austin., 1832 Jan 8 (Box 3, Folder 85)
      3 p. 32 cm. Discusses the current situation in Texas.
  - Bradburn, Juan Davis.
    - ALS to Comandante General, Estados Internos de Oriente, Anahuac, Texas., 1832 Feb 2 (Box 3, Folder 86)
      7 p. 32 cm. On affairs at Anahuac and diffi- culty in collection of customs. Draft of Gen. Teran's reply (3 p.) appended. Copy, transcription, and translation available. See Series II, folder 145.
  - Ugartechea, Domingo de, d.1839.
    - Report of the battle of Velasco to Gen. Mier y Teran, on board the schooner Brazoria., 1832 Jul 1 (Box 3, Folder 87)
      9 p. 32 cm. Pub. Matamoros 1832 with title: Parte que dio el ciudadano ... Ugartechea ... de la accion que sostuvo en el fuerte de Velasco ... Cf. Streeter, Bib. of Texas, no.785.
  - San Antonio, Texas. Gefe Politico.
    - Copy of letter to Antonio Elozua, Comandante Militar, Bexar, Texas., 1832 Jul 26 (Box 3, Folder 88)
      1 p. 30.5 cm. and enclosure 1 p. 30.5 cm Encloses copy of letter from J.A. Mejia to Elozua.
  - Austin, Stephen Fuller, 1793-1836.
    - Copy of letter to Ramon Musquiz, San Felipe de Austin., 1832 Jul 28 (Box 3, Folder 89)
      22 p. 30 cm. Accompanied by a document which appears to be an account of the session of the Ayuntamiento of San Felipe de Austin, 1832 Jul 26. Only a few lines of the letter and document are legible. Relative to the Pronunciamento for the Plan of Vera Cruz and to Santa Anna.
  - Pronunciamento que hace la seccion que guarnecia el Puerto de Velasco y Villa de Brazoria ..., 1832 Aug 26 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    4 p. 32 cm. Signed by Ugartechea and other officers. A copy of the capitulation of Velasco, Jun 29, 1832, is appended.
  - San Antonio, Texas. Jefe Politico.
    - Censo y estadistica. Departamento de Bejar. Ano de 1832, Bejar., 1832 Oct 1
      3 p. 42 cm. Signed: Ramon Musquiz. Copy made in 1834 by R. Chovel.
      See: Oversize, Box 5, folder 152.
  - Bradburn, Juan Davis.
    - Report to Comandante General, Estados Internos de Oriente, n.p., 1832 (Box 3, Folder 91)
      17 p. 30.5 cm. Report of events in Anahuac. Two versions of transcription and three versions of translation available. See Series II, Box 4, folders 146-149.
  - L'Abeille de la Nouvelle Orleans, [1832] (Box 3, Folder 92)
    2 p. 32 cm. Translation of an article from No. 474 of L'Abeille, on events in Texas. Accompanied by 12 p. of notes of the events described.
  - Extracto de las noticias oficiales recibidas sobre la sublevacion de algunos colonos de Tejas, n.p., [1832?] (Box 3, Folder 93)
    4 p. 30.5 cm.
  - Seguin, Juan Angel.
    - Certificate of character for Juan MacMullen, Bejar, Texas., 1833 Apr 24 (Box 3, Folder 94)
      2 p. 32 cm. Signed: Juan Angel Seguin, Ygnacio Arocha, Victoriano Zepeda.
  - Zavala, Lorenzo de, 1788-1836.
    - ALS to Maríano Cubi y Soler, Toluca, Mexico., 1833 May 8 (Box 3, Folder 95)
      2 p. 26 cm.
  - Stone, G.M.
    - ALS to Col. Chambers, Monclova, Mexico., 1834 Mar (Box 3, Folder 96)
      1 p. 33 cm. Directions for regaining health.
  - San Felipe de Austin, Texas. Ayunta- miento.
    - LS to Gefe del Departamento de Bejar, San Felipe de Austin, Texas., 1834 Jun 2 (Box 3, Folder 97)
      3 p. 21 cm. and enclosures 2 p. 31 cm. Signed: Jno.P.Coles, W. Barret Travis. Transmits results of elections in Brazoria.
  - Hernandez, Juan José.
    - LS to Gaspar Flores, Goliad, Texas., 1834 Jun 12 (Box 3, Folder 98)
      3 p. 32 cm. Concerns difficulties in collecting duties from merchants bringing in foreign goods.
  - Coahuila and Texas (State) Gobernador, Sep 23, 1833-Jul 23, 1834 (Vidaurri y Villaseñor).
    - LS to Comandante General los Estados Internos de Oriente, Monclova., 1834 Jun 13 (Box 3, Folder 99)
      2 p. 30 cm. Signed: Francisco Vidaurri y Villaseñor and J. Antonio Padilla. At top of p. 1: Reservado Enclosed: Copy of LS from J.M. Carbajal to Ramon Musquiz, dated 1834 Apr 22, Nacogdoches. 2 p. 30 cm. Concerns the transferring of Indian tribes from the U.S. to Texas by Sam Houston encloses a copy of a letter from J.M. Carbajal relating to this.
  - Almonte, Juan Nepomuceno, 1803-1869.
    - LS to Comandante General, Estados Internos de Oriente, Nacogdoches, Texas., 1834 Jun 16 (Box 3, Folder 100)
      2 p. 29.5 cm. Asks Lemus to come to the frontier and plan a campaign against the Comanches.
    - LS to Comandante General, Estados Internos de Oriente, Nacogdoches, Texas., 1834 Jun 20 (Box 3, Folder 101)
      2 p. 29.5 cm. At top of p. 1: Reservado. Concerns relations with the Indians.
  - Arrcola, Vicente.
    - LS to Comandante General, Estados Internos de Oriente, Monclova, Mexico., 1834 Jun 27 (Box 3, Folder 102)
      4 p. 30.5 cm and enclosure 1 p. 20.5 cm. Enclosed: Copy of LS to Gobernador de este estado. On two new laws which conflict with his military obligations.
  - Almonte, Juan Nepomuceno, 1803-1869.
    - LS to Comandante General, Estados Internos de Oriente, Nacogdoches, Texas, 1834 Jun 30 (Box 3, Folder 103)
      2 p. 29.5 cm. Conditions of the Texas frontier.
  - Goliad, Texas. Comandante Militar.
    - LS (Copy) to James Power, Goliad, Texas, 1834 Jul 23 (Box 3, Folder 104)
      1 p. 30 cm. Signed: M[anuel] Sabariego.
    - ALS to James Power, Goliad, Texas, 1834 Jul 23 (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - ALS to Comandante General, Estados Internos de Oriente, Goliad, Texas, 1834 Jul 30 (Box 3, Folder 106)
      4 p. 31 cm. and enclosure 2 p. 31 cm. On colonists introduced by empresarios James Power and James Hewetson.
    - LS to Comandante General estos Estados, Goliad, Texas, 1834 Jul 30 (Box 3, Folder 107)
      6 p. 30 cm. and enclosures 1 p. 30 cm. Signed: M. Sabariego. Encloses correspondence relating to trouble with new settlers at Refugio.
    - ALS to Comandante General, Estados Internos de Oriente, Goliad, Texas, 1834 Jul 31 (Box 3, Folder 108)
      3 p. 30 cm. and enclosures 5 p. 30 cm. On James Power's colonists at Refugio. Encloses copies of his correspondence with Power and Mordecai Cullen.
    - LS to Comandante General Estos Estados, Goliad, Texas, 1834 Aug 8
      3 p. 33-58.5 cm. Signed: M. Sabariego. Enclosing reports of the families that arrived at Copano.
      See: Oversize, Box 5, folder 153.
  - Brazos, Texas. (Departamento).
    - Report on elections, San Felipe de Austin, Texas., 1834 Aug 24 (Box 3, Folder 109)
      3 p. 32 cm. Signed by Henry Smith and two others.
  - Nacogdoches, Texas.
    - Signed copy of a report on elections, Nacogdoches, Texas., 1834 Aug 24 (Box 3, Folder 110)
      4 p. 31.5 cm. Signed by Vital Flores and four others.
  - San Antonio, Texas
    - Signed copies of 2 reports on elec- tions, San Fernando de Bexar, Texas, 1834 Aug 24 (Box 3, Folder 111)
      3 p. 31 cm. Signed by Antonio Salinas and others.
  - Coahuila and Texas (State) Gobernador, Sep 23 1833-Jul 23, 1834 (Vidaurri y Villaseñor).
    - LS to Comandante General los Estados Internos, Monclova, Mexico., 1834 Aug 28 (Box 3, Folder 112)
      2 p. 30 cm. and enclosure 2 p. 30 cm. Enclosed: Copy of letter to Gefe politico del Departamento de Bexar. On trouble between Ayuntamiento of Goliad and land commissioner J.J. Vidaurri.
  - Coahuila and Texas (State) Gobernador, Aug 30 1834-Mar 12 1835 (Elguezabal).
    - Draft of letter to Gefes del departa- mentos del estado, Monclova, Mexico., 1834 Aug 31 (Box 3, Folder 113)
      2 p. 30.5 cm. Asks for cooperation of Gefes and Ayuntamientos in restoring order in the state.
  - Flores, Gaspar.
    - Executor's bond, San Antonio de Bexar, Texas, 1834 Sep 14 (Box 3, Folder 114)
      3 p. 32 cm. Attested by Ygnacio Chavez and others.
  - San Antonio, Texas. Comandante Militar.
    - LS to Comandante General estos Estados, Bexar, Texas, 1834 Sep 22 (Box 3, Folder 115)
      2 p. 30 cm. and enclosure 2 p. 30 cm. Announces the adhesion of the gar- rison at Bexar to the federalist pronuciamento of Monterrey.
  - Estados Internos de Oriente, Mexico. Comandante General, 1834 (Lemus).
    - AL to Comandante Militar of Goliad, n.p., 1834 Oct 24 (Box 3, Folder 116)
      1 p. 21 cm. Signed with rubric. Attributed to Lemus by H.R. Wagner.
  - San Antonio, Texas. Comandante Militar.
    - LS to Comandante General estos Estados, Bexar, Texas, 1834 Nov 21 (Box 3, Folder 117)
      3 p. 30.5 cm. and enclosure 2 p. 30 cm. Signed: Francisco de Castaneda. Encloses a letter from Ramon Musquiz. On affairs in Texas.
  - Goliad, Texas. Comandante Militar.
    - LS to Comandante General estos Estados, Goliad, Texas, 1834 Nov 23 (Box 3, Folder 118)
      1 p. 30 cm. Signed: M. Sabariego Reports that things are now quiet in Texas.
  - Estados Internos de Oriente, Mexico. Comandante General, 1834-1835 (Cos).
    - Draft of letter to M. Sabariego, Comandante at Goliad, Monterrey, Mexico., 1834 Dec 1 (Box 3, Folder 119)
      1 p. 21.5 cm.
    - Draft of letter to F. Castaneda, Comandante at San Antonio, Monterrey, Mexico., 1834 Dec 4 (Box 3, Folder 120)
      2 p. 21.5 cm.
  - Karankawa nation. Treaties, etc.
    - Tratados celebrados entre la tribu Carankahuas y el captan ciudadano Mariano Corio, n.p., [1834?] (Box 3, Folder 121)
      4 p. 30.5 cm. Copy made in 1834? by M. Sabariego.
  - Goliad, Texas. Comandante Militar.
    - LS to Comandante General estos Estados, Goliad, Texas., 1835 Apr 17
      1 p. 26.5 cm. and enclosure 1 p. 30x42 cm. Signed: M. Sabariego Enclosed: Report of colonization of the settlement of Dolores.
      See: Oversize, Box 5, folder 154.
  - [Estados Internos de Oriente, Mexico. Comandante General, 1834-1835 (Cos)].
    - Drafts of 2 letters to Comandante general, Coahuila and Texas, Boca del rio Bravo., 1835 Jun 8 (Box 3, Folder 122)
      4 p. 21 cm. On troop movements in Texas.
  - Goliad, Texas. Comandante Militar.
    - LS to Comandante General estos Estados, Goliad, Texas., 1835 Jun 25 (Box 3, Folder 123)
      2 p. 30 cm. Signed: M. Sabariego. Concerns the escape of A. Aguero.
  - San Felipe de Austin, Texas. Committee of Safety.
    - LS to Capt. Antonio Tenorio, San Felipe de Austin, Texas, 1835 Jul 15 (Box 3, Folder 124)
      1 p. with address 25 cm. Signed by John R. Jones and six others.
  - Tenorio, Antonio.
    - Copy of ALS to the Committee of Safety, San Felipe de Austin, San Felipe de Austin, Texas, 1835 Jul 15 (Box 3, Folder 125)
      2 p. 27 cm. Asks that the arms he surrendered at Anahuac be returned to him.
  - Gritten, Edward.
    - ALS to Comandante Principal de Coahuila y Texas, San Felipe de Austin, Texas, 1835 Jul 17 (Box 3, Folder 126)
      3 p. 24 cm. On affairs in Texas.
  - Miller, James B. d.1854.
    - LS to Comandante Principal del estado Coahuila y Texas, San Felipe de Austin, Texas, 1835 Jul 17 (Box 3, Folder 127)
      3 p. 24 cm. Another copy laid in. On affairs in Texas.
  - San Felipe de Austin, Texas. Committee of Safety.
    - AL to D.C. Barrett and E. Gritten, San Felipe de Austin, Texas., 1835 Jul 21 (Box 3, Folder 128)
      3 p. 30.5 cm. Signed by J.H. Bell and seven others. Requests that they explain to Gen. Cos the peaceful intentions of the Texans. Text in Spanish; translated by E. Gritten.
  - San Antonio, Texas. Jefe Politico.
    - Copy of LS to Alcalde of Gonzales and to Comandante general of Coahuila and Texas, Bejar, Texas., 1835 Sep 20 (Box 3, Folder 129)
      3 p. 30 cm. Dated 1835 Sep 20, Sep 27. The letter to Gonzales demands return of a cannon loaned to that settlement; the letter to Gen. Ugartechea reports refusal of the demand.
  - Instrucciones a que debe arreglan el Senor Coronel D. Francisco Sandoval, Goliad, Texas., 1835 Oct 5 (Box 3, Folder 130)
    4 p. 31 cm. Military instructions.
  - San Antonio, Texas. Jefe Politico.
    - LS to Alcade of San Antonio, Bexar, Texas., 1835 Oct 24 (Box 3, Folder 131)
      3 p. 21 cm. and enclosures 5 p. 31 cm. Signed: Angel Navarro. Requests investigation of a citizen alleged to have a passport from the Texas rebels. The enclosure is Alcade J.M. Flores' interrogation of Zefirin Ruiz, together with the pass, signed by W.D.C. Hall, by order of S.F. Austin.
  - Pizarro Martinez, Francisco.
    - Duplicate of ALS to President Santa Anna, New Orleans., 1836 Jan 18 (Box 3, Folder 132)
      1 p. 25 cm. Accompanied by: Plan of Military operation against Texas. Tells of the arrival of Austin, Wharton, and Archer and of the loan they have negotiated and says that he is sending along a plan of military operation against Texas.
  - Germain, Z.
    - ALS to Louis Berlandier, New Orleans., 1839 Mar 12 (Box 3, Folder 133)
      3 p. with address 26.5 cm. Attached: Copy of the capitulation between General Cos and Edward Burleson, Dec 10, 1835 (4 p. 26.5 cm.).
  - Coahuila, Mexico. Gobernador, Jan 1842-Mar 1843 (Mejia).
    - 3 LS to José Ignacio Gutierrez, Saltillo, Mexico., 1842 Jul 25-8 (Box 3, Folder 134)
      6 p. 26.5 cm.
  - Burnet, David Gouverneur, 1788-1870.
    - ALS to Mary Austin Holley, Oakland, Texas., 1844 Apr 25 (Box 3, Folder 135)
      4 p. 28 cm. Information on Sam Houston, the battle of San Jacinto, and S.F. Austin for Mrs. Holley's history of Texas.
  - Mejicanos! [Copy of pronunciamento by the garrison of Mazatlan], 1846 May 7 (Box 3, Folder 136)
    12 p. 32 cm. Warns of approaching invasion by the U.S.
  - Severance, Luther, 1797-1855.
    - Translation of a letter to the National Intelligencer, [Washington, D.C.?], 1846 May 12 (Box 3, Folder 137)
      8 p. 27 cm. At end: Traducido para el Liberal Moderado del Tribuno, Periodico de Nueva York - semi-semanario de 30 de Mayo proximo parado. Tells why he did not vote in favor of the resolution which called for money for the war with Mexico.
  - Asuntos de la guerra con E.U.A.
    - Letter to unknown recipient, n.p., 1847 Feb 10 (Box 3, Folder 138)
      Signed with a cross. Title from docket.
  - La República de México, llamada N. España...
    - Document addressed to American occupying forces in Mexico, containing ideas for the reorganization Mexico's civil institutions, Mexico., 1847 Nov 14 (Box 3, Folder 139)
      12 p. Attached letter and translation in response to document. Enclosed are notes on document by César Rodríguez, Curator of the Latin American Collection of Yale University Library, prepared in 1994.
  - 1847. Movimientos de los Americanos, n.p. (Box 3, Folder 140)
    2 p. 28 cm. Title from docket. Notes on movements of American troops in Mexico.
  - Mier y Teran, Manuel de, 1789-1832.
    - Voyage aux populations des rives du Rio Bravo del Norte par le General M.M. Teran. Ecrit par lui-meme, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 3, Folder 141)
      10 p. 32 cm. Unsigned and undated draft. Text in Spanish.
- Transcriptions and Translations, ca.1979-80; Series II; 0.25; (1 box)
  Series II contains transcriptions and translations by by John V. Clay and Alan Probert of letters and documents of Juan [John] Davis Bradburn. The original documents are filed in Series I.
  - BRADBURN, JUAN [JOHN] DAVIS
    - LS to Manuel de Mier y Teran ...
      - Copy, transcription, and translation by John V. Clay., 1980? (Box 4, Folder 142)
        Original in Series I, Box 2, folder 75.
    - Copy of letter to Antonio Elozua ...
      - Transcription and translation by Alan Probert., 1979 Feb 15 (Box 4, Folder 143)
        Original in Series I, Box 2, folder 76.
    - John Austin. ALS to J. D. Bradburn ...
      - Copy, transcription, and translation of the LS from Bradburn to Ge. Teran, 1831 March 4, by John V. Clay., 1980? (Box 4, Folder 144)
        Original in Series I, Box 3, folder 84.
    - ALS to Comandante General, ...
      - Copy, transcription, and translation by John V. Clay., 1980? (Box 4, Folder 145)
        Original in Series I, Box 3, folder 86.
    - Report to Comandante General ...
      - Transcription, first version, by John V. Clay., 1980? (Box 4, Folder 146)
        Original in Series I, Box 3, folder 91. Titled: Memoria que el Comandante Juan Davis Bradburn...
      - Transcription, second version, by John V. Clay., 1980? (Box 4, Folder 147)
      - Translation by John V. Clay., 1980? (Box 4, Folder 148)
        Original in Series I, Box 3, folder 91. Titled: Memoria del Coronel Juan Davis Bradburn sobre los Acontecimientos de Anahuac, 1831-1832.
      - Revised translation by John V. Clay., 1980? (Box 4, Folder 149)
        Original in Series I, Box 3, folder 91. Titled: Memoria del Coronel Juan Davis Bradburn sobre los Acontecimientos de Anahuac, 1831-1832. Enclosed, alternate translation by Alan Probert.
- Oversize, 1.5; (1 box)
  Oversize material contains oversize material from Series I, and in a parallel arrangement.
  - ORIGINAL DOCUMENTS
    Coahuila, Mexico. Governor, 1777-1783 (Ugalde)
    - Proclamation forbidding export of livestock from the province because of acute shortage, Monclova., 1782 Feb 5 (Box 5, Folder 150)
    - Provincias Internas, Mexico. Comandante General, 1805-1813 (Salcedo).
      - Declaration of amnesty to parti- cipants in the Hidalgo rebellion, Chihuahua., 1811 Apr 20 (Box 5, Folder 151)
    - San Antonio, Texas. Jefe Politico.
      - Censo y estadistica. Departamento de Bejar. Ano de 1832, Bejar., 1832 Oct 1 (Box 5, Folder 152)
    - Goliad, Texas. Comandante Militar.
      - LS to Comandante General Estos Estados, Goliad, Texas, 1834 Aug 8 (Box 5, Folder 153)
      - LS to Comandante General estos Estados, Goliad, Texas., 1835 Apr 17 (Box 5, Folder 154)